Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: original artwork
1785-1916
YCGL MSS 26
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(3 boxes)
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork is an artificial collection comprising original artwork that came to Yale from various sources, mostly during the Speck Collection's early decades. It includes some of the Collection's best-known holdings, including an anonymous silhouette made of Goethe in 1786 as well as original sketches and engravings by Goethe. Other artists represented include Wilhelm von Kaulbach, Georg Melchior Kraus, Johann Heinrich Lips, and Moritz Retzsch.
Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired at various times and from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated Materials: William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6), William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Music (YCGL MSS 9), and William A. Speck Collection of Prints (YCGL MSS 11), William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: Theater Ephemera (YCGL MSS 24), and William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: General Ephemera (YCGL MSS 27), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
William A. Speck (1864-1928)
William A. Speck, the son of German immigrants, was born in New York City in 1864. A pharmacist by profession, he amassed the largest Goethe collection outside of Germany. In 1913, he and his collection came from Haverstraw, New York to Yale, where he served as curator of the Speck Collection until his death in 1928. For further biographical information on William A. Speck and a general history and description of the Speck Collection, see the finding aid for the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6).
Scope and Contents
The Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork is an artificial collection comprising original artwork that came to Yale from various sources, mostly during the Speck Collection's early decades. It includes some of the Collection's best-known holdings, including an anonymous silhouette made of Goethe in 1786 as well as original sketches and engravings by Goethe. Other artists represented include Wilhelm von Kaulbach, Georg Melchior Kraus, Johann Heinrich Lips, and Moritz Retzsch.
Facsimiles of several of the items listed here were included in Goetheana: A centenary portfolio of forty-three facsimiles and reproductions of unique or rare items from the William A Speck Collection of Goetheana, published by the Yale University Press in 1932. These facsimiles are not marked as such and can be difficult to distinguish from the originals. The brochure that accompanied the facsimiles contains sometimes dated commentary on each item. Three of the items were published in the series Facsimiles and Reproductions of Unique or Rare Items from the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana in Yale University Library (Yale University Press, 1915-32). The existence of facsimiles is indicated in the list of collection contents.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by name of artist.
Artists -- Germany; Authors, German; German literature -- 19th century; German literature -- 18th century; Drawings (visual works); Engravings (prints); Etchings (prints); Sketches; Silhouettes; Anna Amalia, Duchess of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, 1739-1807; Friedrich, W. (Woldemar), 1846-1910; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 -- Portraits; Gore, Charles, 1729-1807; Hackert, Philipp, 1737-1807; Kaulbach, Wilhelm von, 1804-1874; Kraus, Georg Melchior, 1737-1806; Lips, Johann Heinrich, 1758-1817; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Neureuther, Eugen, 1806-1882; Preller, Friedrich, 1804-1878; Retzsch, Moritz, 1779-1857; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1805; Smirke, Robert, 1752-1845; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
- William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Original Artwork, 1785-1916, undated; 1; (3 boxes)
  - Anna Amalia, Duchess of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, 1739-1807. Two etchings, "Schloss Ettersburg" and untitled (houses on a river or lake) and signed "A" in the plate. (Portfolio XXV, Ettersburg), undated; 2 plates, 13 x 19 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dürer, Albrecht, 1471-1528. "Melancholia," reproduction of the engraving, Stamped: "Facsimile-Reproduction der Reichsdruckerei Berlin.", undated; 24 x 19 cm. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Friedrich, Woldemar, 1846-1910. 3 preliminary pencil sketches for his book Goethes Leben in Bildern (Munich, 1885). "Goethe's Arbeitszimmer," "Weinstock, Goethe-Haus in Weimar," "Altmeister", undated; 20 x 27 cm; 20 x 16 cm.; 20 x 13 cm. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fromann (also Frommann), Alwine. Goethe and Textor family coats of arms, two watercolors, undated; 2 items, 28 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832
    - Coat of arms, ink sketch, undated; 13 x 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      On mount: "Original Federzeichnung von Goethe. Aus dem Nachlaß des Malers Carl W. Lieber in Weimar."
    - Landscape, ink and wash drawing, 1891; 21-27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
      On verso, manuscript authentication dated 1891, by Carl Ruland (1834-1907), director of the Weimar Goethe museum and president of the Goethe Gesellschaft; from the papers of the painter Carl W. Lieber. (Speck facsimile series, 3) Corpus der Goethe-Zeichnungen, vol. 6B, item 23.
    - Two ink sketches, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
      The drawings may have been made during Goethe's association with the brothers F. H. and J. G. Jacobi in the early 1770s. (Portfolio XVIII, Speck facsimile series, 6 as "Two supposedly lost drawings.") Corpus der Goethe-Zeichnungen, vol. 6B, item 261.
    - "Schlossruine," engraving by W. S. Löwe (Berlin, 1819) after a sketch., circa 1810; 19 x24 cm. (plate). (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Corpus der Goethe Zeichnungen, vol. 6B, item 147, dates the sketch ca. 1810, citing the original in the Leizpig University Library.
    - Two engravings after paintings by Alexander Thiele (1685-1752)., undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      With dedications in the plates to Goethe's father and to his Leipzig student friend and later mayor of Leipzig, Christian Gottfried Herrmann (1743-1813).
  - Gore, Charles, 1729-1807. Two seated figures and a dog, silver pencil drawing, signed, 1785; 16 x 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hackert, Philipp, 1737-1807. Rural landscape, ink and wash drawing, signed Ph. Hackert pinx., undated; 19 x 24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kaulbach, Wilhelm von, 1805-74.
    - Lotte cutting bread, surrounded by her siblings, sepia drawing, matted. Reproduced in his Goethe's Frauengestalten of 1871., undated; 19 x 13 cm. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Kaulbach, Wilhelm von, 1805-74. 9 sepia drawings for Schiller's Sämmtliche Werke in einem Bande. Prachtausgabe mit 13 Stahlstichen nach Zeichnungen von Kaulbach (Stuttgart: Cotta, 1840), Marcuse 25a. Bound together., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kraus, Georg Melchior, 1733-1806.
    - "Am Stern bey Weimar," engraving, "Beÿ Weimar, nach Natur gezeichnet," pencil and wash drawing (Portfolio XXVI), "Wilhelmsthal. Herzogl: Weimar: Jagdschloss bey Eisenach," watercolor, undated; 19 x 24.5 cm. (plate), 17 x 23 cm., 18 x 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Three scenes of Weimar and vicinity, handcolored engravings. "II. Ansicht der Sternbrücke"; "III. Ansicht der Bogenbrücke auf den Wiesen"; "IV. Ansicht der Fähre nach dem Sterne." With an uncolored copy of III., 1793; 3 items, each 19 x 25 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Langlois, François, called Ciartres, 1589-1647, publisher. Engraved portrait of the historical Doctor Faustus, after Rembrandt, number 36 from a series of as many portraits. (Portfolio XXXVI), undated; 21 x 19 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lieber, Carl Wilhelm. "Ehringsdorf bei Oberweimar," watercolor., undated; 15 x 19 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lips, Johann Heinrich, 1758-1817. Portrait of Johann Kaspar Lavater (1741-1801), colored engraving in oval border. (Portfolio XIX), undated; 11 x 9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-82. "H.W.L. 'in the clouds' at Göttingen!" ink sketch. Self-portrait as a student in Germany, reading Goethe. (Portfolio, XXXIII), 1829 April 2; 22 x 17 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Naeke (also Näke), Gustav, 1786-1835. Pencil sketches preliminary to his oil painting of Faust und Gretchen (1811), sketches on both sides, matted. With a lithographic reproduction of the finished painting. (Portfolio XLI), undated; 20 x 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Neureuther, Eugen Napoleon, 1806-82. Pencil and ink sketch (border with female figure resembling a ship's figurehead)., undated; 27 x 18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    General note
    Similar in style to the borders found in his page decorations for Randzeichnungen zu Goethe's Ballanden und Romanzen, 1829-39.
  - Northampton Bank, Lehigh County, PA. Note for "Zehn Thaler.", 1836 January 27; 8 x 17 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes portraits of Goethe, Klopstock, Haydn, and Friedrich Wilhelm Herschel (1738-1822), the German-born composer, astronomer, and discoverer of the planet Uranus, who changed his name to William after moving to England early in life.
  - Preller, Friedrich, 1804-1878. Goethe on his deathbed, pencil copy by the artist of his original., 1873; 17 x 13 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    The copy was made in 1873 for Bayard Taylor and later given by his widow to Speck (Portfolio IV).
  - Retzsch, Moritz, 1779-1857. Faust and Gretchen, pencil drawing, undated; 14 x 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scheffler, Rudolf, 1884-1973. Portrait of the German literary scholar Oskar Walzel (1864-1944), pencil drawing, signed and dated 5.11.16, 1916 May 11; 33 x 25 cm., matted. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Smirke, Robert, 1752-1845. Scene from Werther, showing Werther, Lotte, and Albert in a garden, pencil and sepia wash drawing, undated; 11.5 x 7.5 cm., matted. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Custodial History
    Purchased on the E. J. Beinecke Fund, late 1960s or early 1970s.
  - [Speck, William A. (?), subject], Silhouette, undated; 12 cm., mounted on sheet, 33 x 25 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - [Werther] "Goethe und Lotte, die Beiden in Werters Freuden 1775," ink silhouette, octagon in oval mount, undated; 20 x 16.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Goethe im J. 1786." Anonymous silhouette., undated; 13 x 10 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    On verso: "le Conseillez privé de Weÿmar. Goethe. Carlsbad. 1786." (Portfolio I; Speck facsimile series, 1; Speck Collection bookplate)